countries like India, Russia, South Africa, Brazil and even China are falling below that seven percent number and, in many cases, actually regressing. Economic growth matters. With economic growth, countries and societies enter into a virtuous cycle of upward mobility, opportunity and improved living standards. Without growth, countries contract and atrophy, not just in the annals of economic statistics but also in the meaning of life and how lives are lived. Economic growth matters powerfully for the individual. If growth wanes, the risk to human progress and the risk of political and social instability rises, and societies become dimmer, coarser and smaller. The context matters. And countries in emerging markets do not need to grow at the same rates as developed countries. Now, I know some of you in this room find this to be a risky proposition. There are some people here who will turn around and be quite disillusioned by what's happened around the world and basically ascribe that to economic growth. You worry about the overpopulation of the planet. And looking at the UN's recent statistics and projections that the world will have 11 billion people on the planet before it plateaus in 2100,
se encuentran India, Rusia, Sudáfrica, Brasil y China que no alcanzan el 7 % y en muchos casos retroceden. El crecimiento de la economía importa. Con el crecimiento, los países y las sociedades ingresan en un ciclo virtuoso de movilidad ascendente, de oportunidad y mejores niveles de vida. Sin el crecimiento, los países se contraen y se atrofian, no solo en los anales de estadísticas económicas también en el significado de la vida y en cómo es vivida. El crecimiento económico afecta profundamente al individuo. Si el crecimiento disminuye, se pone en riesgo el progreso humano y aumenta el riesgo de inestabilidad política y social, las sociedades se apagan, se vuelven vulgares y empequeñecen. El contexto es importante. Los países de mercados emergentes no necesitan crecer al mismo nivel que los países desarrollados. Sé que a algunos de Uds. le parecerá una proposición riesgosa. Hay algunos aquí que se sentirán desilusionados por lo que pasa en el mundo y se lo atribuyen a la economía. Se preocupan por la superpoblación del planeta. Observando las recientes estadísticas de la ONU que habrá 11 000 millones de personas en el mundo antes de que decline en el 2100,
you're concerned about what that does to natural resources -- arable land, potable water, energy and minerals. You are also concerned about the degradation of the environment. And you worry about how man, embodied in the corporate globalist, has become greedy and corrupt. But I'm here to tell you today that economic growth has been the backbone of changes in living standards of millions of people around the world. And more importantly, it's not just economic growth that has been driven by capitalism. The definition of capitalism, very simply put, is that the factors of production, such as trade and industry, capital and labor, are left in the hands of the private sector and not the state. It's really essential here that we understand that fundamentally the critique is not for economic growth per se but what has happened to capitalism. And to the extent that we need to create economic growth over the long term, we're going to have to pursue it with a better form of economic stance. Economic growth needs capitalism, but it needs it to work properly. And as I mentioned a moment ago, the core of the capitalist system has been defined by private actors. And even this, however, is a very simplistic dichotomy. Capitalism: good; non-capitalism: bad. When in practical experience, capitalism is much more of a spectrum. And we have countries such as China, which have practiced more state capitalism,
Uds. se preocupan porque esto puede afectar a los recursos naturales como tierra fértil, agua potable, energía y minerales. También se preocupan por la degradación del medio ambiente y se preocupan por cómo el hombre, encarnado en las corporaciones mundiales, se ha vuelto ambicioso y corrupto. Pero estoy aquí para decirles que el crecimiento económico ha sido el eje de los cambios en los estándares de vida de millones de personas en el mundo. Y, lo más importante, no es solo el crecimiento de la economía conducido por el capitalismo. La definición de capitalismo, sencillamente, es que los factores de producción, como el comercio, la industria, el capital y el empleo, están en manos del sector privado y no en el Estado. Es esencial que comprendamos que fundamentalmente la crítica no es a la economía y su crecimiento sino al capitalismo. Para provocar un crecimiento en la economía a largo plazo, tendremos que conseguirlo con una mejor postura económica. El crecimiento económico necesita al capitalismo, y trabajar adecuadamente. Como mencioné hace un momento, el núcleo del sistema capitalista ha sido definido por el sector privado. Y esto es una dicotomía muy simplista. El capitalismo es bueno; el no capitalismo es malo. En la experiencia práctica, el capitalismo es un amplio espectro. Hay países como China, que han aplicado más el capitalismo de estado,
and we have countries like the Unites States which are more market capitalist. Our efforts to critique the capitalist system, however, have tended to focus on countries like China that are in fact not blatantly market capitalism. However, there is a real reason and real concern for us to now focus our attentions on purer forms of capitalism, particularly those embodied by the United States. This is really important because this type of capitalism has increasingly been afforded the critique that it is now fostering corruption and, worse still, it's increasing income inequality -- the idea that the few are benefiting at the expense of the many. The two really critical questions that we need to address
y hay países como Estados Unidos que son capitalistas de mercado. Nuestros esfuerzos para criticar el sistema capitalista se han enfocado en países como China que no son completamente capitalistas de mercado. Sin embargo, hay una razón y una preocupación para enfocarnos en formas más puras de capitalismo, particularmente las practicadas en EE.UU. Esto es muy importante porque este tipo de capitalismo ha sido fuertemente acusado de promover la corrupción y también de incrementar la inequidad de ingresos; la idea de que unos pocos se benefician a expensas de la mayoría. Las preguntas más importantes que debemos abordar son:
is how can we fix capitalism so that it can help create economic growth but at the same time can help to address social ills. In order to think about that framing, we have to ask ourselves, how does capitalism work today? Very simplistically, capitalism is set on the basis of an individual utility maximizer -- a selfish individual who goes after what he or she wants. And only after they've maximized their utility do they then decide it's important to provide support to other social contracts. Of course, in this system governments do tax, and they use part of their revenues to fund social programs, recognizing that government's role is not just regulation but also to be arbiter of social goods. But nevertheless, this framework --
¿Cómo arreglar el capitalismo para que pueda ayudarnos en el crecimiento de la economía y que nos ayude a resolver los problemas sociales? Para pensar en esta idea tenemos que preguntarnos, ¿cómo funciona hoy el capitalismo? Simplemente, el capitalismo se basa en aumentar la utilidad individual; un individuo egoísta que va detrás de lo que quiere. Solo después de que su utilidad haya aumentado, deciden que es importante brindar apoyo a otros contratos sociales. En este sistema los gobiernos cobran impuestos, y usan parte de sus ingresos para financiar programas sociales, aceptando que el rol del gobierno no es solo la regulación sino también ser juez de los bienes sociales. Sin embargo, este marco de referencia
this two-stage framework --
de dos etapas
is the basis from which we must now start to think about how we can improve the capitalist model. I would argue that there are two sides to this challenge. First of all, we can draw on the right-wing policies to see what could be beneficial for us to think about how we can improve capitalism. In particular, right-leaning policies have tended to focus on things like conditional transfers, where we pay and reward people for doing the things
es la base por donde debemos empezar a pensar en mejorar el modelo capitalista. Yo diría que hay dos aspectos en este desafío. Primero, podemos tomar las políticas de la derecha y ver qué sería beneficioso para lograr mejorar el capitalismo. En particular, las políticas de derecha suelen hacer hincapié en las transferencias condicionales, donde pagamos y premiamos a personas por hacer cosas
that we actually think can help enhance economic growth. For example, sending children to school, parents could earn money for that, or getting their children inoculated or immunized,
que creemos que pueden ayudarnos a hacer crecer la economía. Por ejemplo, al enviar a los niños al colegio, los padres pueden ganar dinero, o al mantener a sus hijos vacunados e inmunes,
parents could get paid for doing that. Now, quite apart from the debate on whether or not we should be paying people to do what we think they should do anyway, the fact of the matter is that pay for performance has actually yielded some positive results in places like Mexico, in Brazil and also in pilot programs in New York. But there are also benefits and significant changes underway on left-leaning policies. Arguments that government should expand its role and responsibility so that it's not so narrowly defined and that government should be much more of an arbiter of the factors of production have become commonplace with the success of China. But also we've started to have debates about how the role of the private sector
los padres podrían recibir dinero. Más allá del debate de si debemos o no pagarle a las personas por hacer lo que pensamos que deberían hacer, lo que importa es que pagar por lo producido ha dado algunos resultados positivos en lugares como México, en Brasil y en programas piloto en Nueva York. Aunque también hay beneficios y cambios importantes en las políticas de la izquierda. Discusiones de que el gobierno debería expandir su rol y responsabilidad para no estar tan limitado y que el gobierno debería ser más un juez del factor de producción se ha vuelto muy común con el éxito de China. Pero también, hemos empezado a debatir sobre que el rol del sector privado
should move away from just being a profit motive and really be more engaged in the delivery of social programs. Things like the corporate social responsibility programs, albeit small in scale, are moving in that right direction. Of course, left-leaning policies have also tended to blur the lines between government, NGOs and private sector. Two very good examples of this are the 19th-century United States, when the infrastructure rollout was really about public-private partnerships. More recently, of course,
debería dejar de ser solo obtener ganancia e involucrarse más en contribuir a programas sociales. Al igual que los programas de responsabilidad social empresaria, aunque en menor escala, se están moviendo en esa dirección. Por supuesto que las políticas de izquierda han borrado los límites entre el gobierno, las ONGs y el sector privado. Dos ejemplos de esto son los Estados Unidos del siglo XIX, cuando el despliegue de infraestructura se basó en asociaciones públicas y privadas. Recientemente,
the advent of the Internet has also proven to the world that public and private can work together for the betterment of society. My fundamental message to you is this: We cannot continue to try and solve the world economic growth challenges by being dogmatic and being unnecessarily ideological. In order to create sustainable, long-term economic growth and solve the challenges and social ills that continue to plague the world today, we're going to have to be more broad-minded about what might work. Ultimately, we have to recognize that ideology is the enemy of growth. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: I want to ask a couple of questions, Dambisa, because one could react to your last sentence by saying growth is also an ideology, it's possibly the dominant ideology of our times. What do you say to those who react that way? DM: Well, I think that that's completely legitimate, and I think that we're already having that discussion. There's a lot of work going on around happiness and other metrics being used for measuring people's success and improvements in living standards. And so I think that we should be open to what could deliver improvements in people's living standards and continue to reduce poverty around the world. BG: So you're basically pleading for rehabilitating growth, but the only way for that happen without compromising the capacity of the earth, to take us on a long journey, is for economic growth somehow to decouple from the underlying use of resources. Do you see that happening? DM: Well, I think that I'm more optimistic about human ability and ingenuity. I think if we start to constrain ourselves using the finite, scarce and depleting resources that we know today, we could get quite negative and quite concerned about the way the world is. However, we've seen the Club of Rome, we've seen previous claims that the world would be running out of resources, and it's not to argue that those things are not valid. But I think, with ingenuity we could see desalination, I think we could reinvest in energy, so that we can actually get better outcomes. And so in that sense, I'm much more optimistic about what humans can do. BG: The thing that strikes me
la llegada de Internet ha demostrado al mundo que lo público y lo privado pueden ayudar juntos a la sociedad. Mi mensaje principal para Uds. es: No podemos seguir tratando de resolver los desafíos económicos con dogmas o con ideología innecesaria. Para crear un crecimiento sustentable de la economía a largo plazo y resolver los problemas sociales que siguen apoderándose del mundo, tendremos que abrir la mente a lo que puede funcionar. Finalmente, tenemos que aceptar que la ideología es enemiga del crecimiento. Gracias. (Aplausos) BG: Quiero hacer unas preguntas, Dambisa, porque podríamos responder a lo último que dijiste que el crecimiento es una ideología, y que es posiblemente la ideología dominante de hoy. ¿Qué le dirías a los que te dijeran eso? DM: Bueno, creo que eso es verdad, y creo que estamos discutiendo sobre eso. Hay mucho trabajo con respecto a la felicidad y otros métodos usados para medir el éxito de la gente y las mejoras en los niveles de vida. Así que creo que debemos estar abiertos a lo que podría mejorar el nivel de vida de las personas y seguir reduciendo la pobreza en el mundo. BG: Estás pidiendo un crecimiento que rehabilite, pero la única forma de que suceda sin comprometer la capacidad del planeta de perdurar en el tiempo, es que el crecimiento económico en cierta forma se desacople del uso de recursos subyacente. ¿Notas que sucede eso? DM: Soy optimista acerca de la habilidad y el ingenio humanos. Creo que si nos limitamos al uso de recursos escasos que conocemos hoy, seríamos pesimistas y estaríamos preocupados por cómo es el mundo. Sin embargo, hemos visto al Club de Roma, hemos visto reclamos anteriores de que el mundo se quedará sin recursos y sabemos que eso no es válido. Pero con ingenio podríamos ver la desalinización, podríamos reinvertir en energía, para obtener mejores resultados. Por eso, en ese sentido, soy optimista acerca de la capacidad humana. BG: Lo que me sorprende
about your proposals for rehabilitating growth and taking a different direction is that you're kind of suggesting to fix capitalism with more capitalism -- with putting a price tag on good behavior as incentive or developing a bigger role for business in social issues. Is that what you're suggesting? DM: I'm suggesting we have to be open-minded. I think it is absolutely the case that traditional models of economic growth are not working the way we would like them to. And I think it's no accident that today the largest economy in the world, the United States, has democracy, liberal democracy, as it's core political stance and it has free market capitalism -- to the extent that it is free -- free market capitalism as its economic stance. The second largest economy is China. It has deprioritized democracy and it has state capitalism, which is a completely different model.
de tus propuestas de crecimiento rehabilitador y tomando una dirección diferente es que estás sugiriendo arreglar el capitalismo con más capitalismo, poniendo un precio al buen comportamiento como incentivo o desarrollando un rol mayor en los asuntos sociales. ¿Es esto lo que sugieres? DM: Sugiero que seamos abiertos de mente. Creo que ocurre que los modelos tradicionales de crecimiento económico no funcionan como nos gustaría. Creo que no es casualidad que la economía más grande del mundo, la de Estados Unidos, tenga democracia, una democracia liberal, como núcleo de su posición política y que tenga capitalismo de mercado libre, al punto de que es libre, capitalismo de mercado libre como postura económica. La segunda economía más grande es China. No ha priorizado la democracia y tiene un capitalismo de Estado, que plantea un modelo distinto.
These two countries, completely different political models and completely different economic models, and yet they have the same income inequality number measured as a Gini coefficient. I think those are the debates we should have, because it's not clear at all what model we should be adopting, and I think there needs to be much more discourse and much more humility about what we know and what we don't know. BG: One last question. The COP21 is going on in Paris. If you could send a tweet to all the heads of state and heads of delegations there, what would you say? DM: Again, I would be very much about being open-minded.
Estos dos países, con modelos políticos completamente diferentes y modelos económicos completamente diferentes, tienen cifras iguales de desigualdad en el ingreso medido como coeficiente Gini. Creo que deberíamos discutir sobre eso, porque no está del todo claro qué modelo deberíamos adoptar, y creo que debería haber más diálogo y más humildad acerca de lo que sabemos e ignoramos. BG: Última pregunta, el COP21 está en París. Si pudieras enviar un tuit a los jefes de Estado y a las delegaciones que están allí, ¿qué les dirías? DM: Les hablaría de ser abiertos de mente.
As you're aware, the issues around the environmental concerns have been on the agenda many times now -- in Copenhagen, '72 in Stockholm -- and we keep revisiting these issues partly because there is not a fundamental agreement, in fact there's a schism between what the developed countries believe and want and what emerging market countries want. Emerging market countries need to continue to create economic growth so that we don't have political uncertainty in the those countries. Developed countries recognize that they have a real, important responsibility not only just to manage their CO2 emissions and some of the degradation that they're contributing to the world, but also as trendsetters in R&D. And so they have to come to the table as well. But in essence, it cannot be a situation where we start ascribing policies to the emerging markets without developed countries themselves also taking quite a swipe at what they're doing both in demand and supply in developed markets. BG: Dambisa, thank you for coming to TED. DM: Thank you very much. (Applause)
Como saben, las cuestiones relativas al medio ambiente han estado en la agenda muchas veces, en Copenhague, en el '72 en Estocolmo, y seguimos revisando estos temas en parte porque no hay un acuerdo, hay una escisión entre lo que piensan los países desarrollados y lo que quieren los países de mercados emergentes. Los países con mercados emergentes deben hacer crecer su economía para que no tengamos inseguridad política en esos países. Los países desarrollados reconocen que tienen una responsabilidad importante no solo de controlar sus emisiones de CO2 y a parte de la degradación a la que contribuyen en el mundo sino también la de marcar tendencia en I+D. Así que tienen que discutir eso también. Pero en esencia, no puede haber una asignación de políticas a los mercados emergentes sin que los países desarrollados observen lo que hacen en términos de oferta y demanda en los mercados desarrollados. BG: Dambisa, gracias por venir a TED. DM: Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)